<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2545 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2545.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4271 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4291 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5925 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5925.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7454 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7454.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7606 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7606.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-white-linklocalnh-00" ipr="trust200902">

<front>

<title>Link Local Next Hop Handling for BGP</title>

<author fullname="Russ White" initials="R.W." surname="White">
<organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
<address>
<postal><street></street></postal>
<email>russ@riw.us</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Donald Sharp" initials="D.S." surname="Sharp">
<organization>Cumulus Networks</organization>
<address>
<postal><street></street></postal>
<email>sharpd@cumulusnetworks.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Dinesh Dutt" initials="D.D." surname="Dutt">
<organization>Stardust Consulting</organization>
<address>
<postal><street></street></postal>
<email>ddutt@hobbesdutt.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Biswajit Sadhu" initials="B.S" surname="Sadhu">
<organization>VMWare</organization>
<address>
<postal><street></street></postal>
<email>biswajit.sadhu@gmail.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Jeff Tantsura" initials="J.T." surname="Tantsura">
<organization>Apstra, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal><street></street></postal>
<email>jefftant.ietf@gmail.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<date month="October" year="2019" />

<area>Routing</area>
<workgroup>Interdomain Routing</workgroup>

<abstract>

<t>BGP, described in <xref target="RFC4271" />, was originally designed to provide reachability between domains and between the edges of a domain. As such, BGP assumes the next hop towards any reachable destination may not reside on the advertising speaker, but rather may either be through a router connected to the same subnet as the speaker, or through a router only reachable by traversing multiple hops through the network. Because of this, BGP does not recognize the use of IPv6 link local addresses, as described in <xref target="RFC4291" />, as a valid next hop for forwarding purposes.</t>

<t>However, BGP speakers are now often deployed on point-to-point links in networks where multihop reachability of any kind is not assumed or desired (all next hops are assumed to be the speaker reachable through a directly connected point-to-point link). This is common, for instance, in data center fabrics. In these situations, a global IPv6 address is not required for the advertisement of reachability information; in fact, providing global IPv6 addresses in these kinds of networks can be detrimental to Zero Touch Provisioning (ZTP).</t>

<t>This draft standardizes the operation of BGP over a point-to-point link using link local IPv6 addressing only.</t>

</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  
<section title="Introduction">

<t>BGP, described in <xref target="RFC4271" />, was originally designed to provide reachability between domains and between the edges of a domain. As such, BGP assumes the next hop towards any reachable destination may not reside on the advertising speaker, but rather may either be through a router connected to the same subnet as the speaker, or through a router only reachable by traversing multiple hops through the network. Because of this, BGP does not recognize the use of IPv6 link local addresses, as described in <xref target="RFC4271" />, as a valid next hop for forwarding purposes.</t>

<t>However, BGP speakers are now often deployed on point-to-point links in networks where multihop reachability of any kind is not assumed or desired (all next hops are assumed to be the speaker reachable through a directly connected point-to-point link). This is common, for instance, in data center fabrics. In these situations, a global IPv6 address is not required for the advertisement of reachability information; in fact, providing global IPv6 addresses in these kinds of networks can be detrimental to Zero Touch Provisioning (ZTP).</t>

</section>
<!-- end of introduction -->
     
<section title="Changes to BGP Next Hop Attribute to Support Link Local on Point-to-Point">

<t><xref target="RFC2545" />, section 2, notes link local IPv6 addresses are not generally suitable for use in the Next Hop field of the MP_REACH_NLRI. In order to support the many uses of link local addresses, however, <xref target="RFC2545" /> constructs the Next Hop field in IPv6 route advertisements by setting the length of the field to 32, and including both a link local and global IPv6 address in the resulting enlarged field. In this way, the receiving BGP speaker can use the global IPv6 address to build local forwarding information, and the link local address for ICMPv6 redirects, etc. <xref target="RFC2545" /> does not, however, provide an explanation for situations where there is only a link local IPv6 address in the Next Hop field of the MP_REACH_NLRI. The result is each implementation that supports link local peering along with forwarding to a link local address has implemented the construction of the Next Hop field in the MP_REACH_NLRI when there is only a link local address available in slightly different ways.</t>

<t>If an implementation intends to send a single link local forwarding address in the Next Hop field of the MP_REACH_NLRI, it MUST set the length of the Next Hop field to 16 and include only the IPv6 link local address in the Next Hop field.</t>

<t>If an implementation intends to send both a link local and global IPv6 forwarding address in the Next Hop field of the MP_REACH_NLRI, it MUST set the length of the Next Hop field to 32 and include both the IPv6 link local and global IPv6 forwarding addresses in the Next Hop field. If both link local and global IPv6 forwarding addresses are carried in the Next Hop Field, the speaker SHOULD provide a local configuration option to determine which address is preferred for forwarding.</t>

</section>
<!-- end of changes to BGP next hop section -->

<section title="Receiver Processing of IPv6 Link Local Forwarding Addresses">

<t>On receiving an MP_REACH_NLRI with a Next Hop length of 16, implementations SHOULD form the forwarding information using the IPv6 next hop contained in the Next Hop field, regardless of whether it is a link local or globally reachable IPv6 address.</t>

<t>Implementations MAY check the validity of any IPv6 link local address used to calculate forwarding information by insuring the address is in the local neighbor table for the interface on which the BGP update was received (or through which the BGP speaker from which the update was received is reachable). There MUST be a configuration option to enable/disable this check.</t>

<t>Note: It is possible that checking the IPv6 neighbor table for the existence or validity of a link local next hop may make instances where a link is being overwhelmed through some form of Deinal of Service (DoS) attack worse than they would otherwise be. If the IPv6 neighbor cache is overrun in a way that causes the link local address being used for BGP peering to be removed from the table, which is possible through an on-link DoS attack, any fresh BGP update will cause the entire peering session to fail if the implementation is checking the validity of link local next hops as described above. Operators should carefully assess the use of validation against the local IPv6 neighbor table to determine if it is appropriate for any particular peering session.</t>

</section>

<section title="Error handling">

<t>A BGP speaker receiving an MP_REACH_NLRI with the length of the Next Hop Field set to 32, where the update contains anything other than a link local IPv6 address and a global IPv6 address, SHOULD consider this a malformed UPDATE message, and proceed as described in the following paragraphs. In order to support backwards compatibility with existing implementations, an implementation MAY ignore a second link local IPv6 address or 0::0/0 included with an IPv6 link local address when the length of the Next Hop Field is set to 32; in this case, the implementation SHOULD report the existence of this additional information so the operator can correct the sending BGP implementation.</t>

<t>If the Next Hop field is malformed, the implementation MUST handle the mailformed UPDATE message using the approach of "treat-as-withdraw", as described in section 7.3 of <xref target="RFC7606" />. It MAY send a NOTIFICATION message as described in section 4 of <xref target="RFC4271" />, using the UPDATE error message code (8 - Invalid NEXT_HOP Attribute) indicating there is an invalid NEXT_HOP field</t>

<t>If the Next Hop field is properly formed, but the link local next hop is not reachable (as determined by an examination of the IPv6 neighbor table), the implementation MAY handle the mailformed UPDATE message using the approach of "treat-as-withdraw", as described in section 7.3 of <xref target="RFC7606" /> (see note above on checking the local neighbor table for the correctness of the next hop). The implementation MAY send a NOTIFICATION message as described in section 4 of <xref target="RFC4271" /> using the UPDATE error message code (TBA), indicating a link local address was included in the MP_REACH_NLRI, but the link local address included cannot be reached. As this could indicate a security breach of some type (see the security considerations section below), the operator SHOULD have a local configuration option to terminate the peering session until manual intervention is initiated.</t>

</section>
<!-- end of receiver processing of IPv6 link local forwarding addresses -->

<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>The authors would like to thank Don Slice, Jeff Haas, and John Scudder for their contributions to this draft.</t>

</section>
<!-- end of acknolwedgments section -->

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This memo requests IANA assign a number from the "Error Subcodes" registry defined in the IANA Considerations section in <xref target="RFC4271" />. This allocation will be for a new UPDATE error subcode, code (TBA), with a value of "Unreachable Link Local Address."</t>

</section>
<!-- end of iana considerations section -->

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

<t>The mechanism described in this draft can be used as a component of ZTP for building BGP adjacencies across point-to-point links. This method, then, can be used by an attacker to form a peering session with a BGP speaker, ultimately advertising incorrect routing information into a routing domain in order to misdirect traffic or cause a denial of service. By using link local IPv6 addresses, the attacker would be able to forego the use of a valid IPv6 address within the domain, making such an attack easier.</t>

<t>Operators SHOULD carefully consider security when deploying link local addresses for BGP peering. Operators SHOULD filter traffic on links where BGP peering is not intended to occur to prevent speakers from accepting BGP session requests, as well as other mechanisms described in <xref target="RFC7454" />.</t>
     
<t>Operators MAY also use some form of cryptographic validation on links within the network to prevent unauthorized devices from forming BGP peering sessions. Authentication, such as the TCP authentication described in <xref target="RFC5925" />, may provide some relief, if it is present and correctly configured. However, the distribution and management of keys in an environment where global addresses are not present on BGP speakers may be challenging.</t>
     
<t>Operators also MAY instruct a BGP peer which has received an UPDATE with an unreachable NEXT_HOP to disable the peering session over which the invalid NEXT_HOP was received pending manual intervention.</t>

</section>
<!-- end of security considerations -->

</middle>

<back>
<!-- References split into informative and normative -->

<!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
(for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

<references title="Normative References">
<!--?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
&RFC2119;
&RFC2545;
&RFC4271;
&RFC4291;
&RFC5925;
&RFC7454;
&RFC7606;
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
&RFC2629;
&RFC3552;

</references>

</back>
</rfc>
